<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>algae whisperer</title>
 <link href="/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/"/>
 <updated>2020-10-11T11:39:17-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Cameron MacNair</name>
   <email>algaewhisperer@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Pieces - Everything Sings pt1 (a series)</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/10/11/pieces/"/>
   <updated>2020-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/11/pieces</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h6 id=&quot;to-engage-with-silence-or-rather-the-idea-of-silence-is-a-particular-type-of-romance-that-can-unsettle-and-resettle-your-human-ness-to-truly-listen-and-to-separate-your-triumphs-from-perceived-sound-is-to-become-lustful-with-the-connection-between-you-and-your-world&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;To engage with silence, or rather the idea of silence, is a particular type of romance that can unsettle and resettle your human-ness. To truly listen and to separate your triumphs from perceived sound is to become lustful with the connection between you and your world.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find a space where you feel comfortable and safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identify the sounds you hear - whether it’s the sound of the traffic outside, a television or dishwasher, or the birds calling to one another, or all of them at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are fleeting, are they not? Even if they sustain, they will not sustain forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now find the sound with the highest perceived register. It’s full of oscillations isn’t it? A bird’s call is cyclical, a dishwasher resonates in many places with fluid, and the hum of traffic is many people in many cars in machines of many sounds. Each object is a multiplicity of objects and they harmonize and fit together in a way that no other sounds do in any other moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have found a sound. And if it ends, find another. And if that ends, find peace and gratitude with the fleeting nature of experience you have just observed. Rest on that feeling and then start again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engage deeply with this sound by breaking it apart and finding its harmonics, whether dissonant or not. Let it cycle through it’s permutations and circle back again. Try to identify when the sound repeats a tone or timbre. This is time folding into itself. This is your human-ness and its linear nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While focussing on this sound, synchronize your breathing to its oscillations. Find some pattern that you can comfortably breathe to. Continue doing this until you feel your heartbeat start to shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is this connection you share with the object? Do you find it welcoming?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continue to listen, breathe, and focus on the connection you share with the sound producing object. If it’s unwelcome, try to identify why it is unwelcome and then remove that piece by piece. After all, it’s just a sound and you are the one reacting to it. You will soon find all sounds peaceful, unique, and welcoming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have felt enough, let go of this object and notice another. One by one, let all the sounds in and return to where you started - as a piece in a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;this-article-is-one-of-many-to-come-in-a-series-called-everything-sings-that-explores-the-nature-of-engendering-music-through-listening&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This article is one of many to come in a series called Everything Sings that explores the nature of engendering music through listening&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Music To Challenge You</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/10/08/music-to-challenge-you/"/>
   <updated>2020-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/08/music-to-challenge-you</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The act of listening is the act of reasoning. Passive listening practices strengthens passive reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When listening to recorded music, the affect it has on the reader pulls them along in some direction. It can be any forcefulness in any direction across the planes of emotion, physical response, and inwards-ness. Music takes you on a journey, as they say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You, the sailor in the rough sea, gazes out to your territorial bounds, and finds the waves fierce. “To adventure!” You say as you embark forward. Or “To hell with that!” as you retreat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music To Challenge You, I’ll call it. An approaching wave that your boat was not built for. So why not build a surfboard, and find sustenance through the joy of surfing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes your board will lift and drop gently and smoothly, as you cascade down the perfect crest. Other times you will be plummeted forward, body dragged along by a cord attached to the board, gasping for air when you might. But you will always get up and that experience will shape you. Some days you may not have any waves at all - but you are still on your board in the middle of the sea and isn’t that peacefulness something to behold? Doesn’t it explain the waves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These experiences provide you a context into how other people surf, why they surf, and how it is one of the things that makes them tick tick tick along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give yourself to the waves and live freely in the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really is the act of observing causation and applying meaning to it? Did the new houseplant disappear because you figure your cat ate it? How do you know you have a cat? This is what reasoning is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through reasoning we define ourselves and find ourselves in the world. Let’s talk about these reasonings as nodes. Music, as in, music that music reaches to be, is the connections between those nodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now what is passive reasoning? It’s letting reasoning envelop you without any interjection to yourself. It’s accepting, trusting, and absorbing the reasoning in the experiences of your life. “You and your stomach!” as Nietzsche might interrupt me to say. By not questioning the process of reasoning, we end up with a feedback loop of reasoning, resulting in hateful, divisive, or obsessive compulsiveness. If these ‘nodes’ are rooted in the self, and music is the connection of those nodes, then what is passive listening?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passive listening strengthens the nodes of reason without any question, opposition, or friction. Through active listening, there is stronger friction into considering what is right and what is wrong. And through this friction we can develop our morals and our loving minds. Many listener’s of today will either passively listen or passively reject without any question. Sometimes this is based in moral goodness (see PLUR) but it is narrow and temperamental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you step out into the world (or step in) try to engage deeply and fondly with listening. If the thought comes to tell you that some sound is right or some sound is wrong (is the car alarm outside your window annoying you?) think critically and think with less of your human-ness. Listen to the nuance as you realize your projections into the sounds you find. You find yourself, don’t you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I promise you - the waves are super nice today.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Vulnerability, the (rhizomatic?) nature of music, and product thinking</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/10/05/vulnerability/"/>
   <updated>2020-10-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/05/vulnerability</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.upress.umn.edu/book-division/books/a-thousand-plateaus&quot;&gt;A Thousand Plateaus, Capitalism and Schizophrenia&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Gilles Deleuze&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Félix Guattari&lt;/em&gt;. This work is about modes of knowledge and rhizomatic philosophy. Particularly, the multiplicities of being that are shared among us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hidden deep beneath our higher level operating state of perceived causation, is a network of connections that binds us and our things to all other things. And where we end up finding ourselves, is no where but in the connections, rooted to a greater system of entropy and decay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rhizome, an organic structure of all the organic, mutable in state but immutable in process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now.. how is this state of being communicated and observed? I think it’s through music (or from a more spiritual terminology, the reach for music).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lespressesdureel.com/EN/ouvrage.php?id=8071&quot;&gt;The Music to Come&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;François J. Bonnet&lt;/em&gt; states that music is not in fact music, but it’s an avatar for itself. Music as it exists and is experienced, is a grasp at the unconscious grasping at its connections. Music, the one that we hear, is an idea, or rather a notation, of the music that exists in this space, the rhizome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you closed your eyes and imagined the feeling you get from that particular piece of music? Is that feeling tangible in the music itself, or is it engendered with you, the listener? Is that feeling discreetly limited to transcriptions of notation, or the conversations about notation? Is it rules that are followed or broken?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now consider the relationship between the creator(s) and the instruments. Is that feeling a derivative of that one and only permutation? Is it universally shared or is it a perceived structure from the vast nothingness?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more I turn this over to myself, and look inside me to find what is true, I do agree that music is an avatar, a rendering, for the idea of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding Music Theory and the common modern music. The most common forms of ‘music avatars’ today are expressions of Imperialism and the western capitalist movement. Music theory, ‘how to do music and how not to do it’, are direct reflections on (particularly white) history, rather than free emphatic expression. For example, the strict music structure engendered by the genre of Electronic Dance Music is a gesture of a reward of a product, placed in a historical context (which might happen to be now). This ‘product’ being the listener’s expectations and predictions, exposed without challenge or remorse, rising and falling without actually rising and falling. I will not comment on the measure of value of this genre, that is another discussion entirely, but I would like to address the lack of vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be truly expressive is to be vulnerable. The musical gestures of strict alignment and structure do not embrace vulnerability, but a system of security, familiarity and expectation matching. This is not inherently better or worse, but it is product of product and is defined by a value that cannot be applied universally. Not that dance music can’t be vulnerable (in fact it can be extremely vulnerable..), but the trend I see today is to move away from vulnerability. Is this a reflection of our zeitgeist?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
